A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, Minutes and Annual Reports, SG 16.1 and SG 16.2 FA120
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, Minutes and Annual Reports, SG 16.1 and SG 16.2
1913-1991
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
FA120
42.3 Cubic Feet
Biographical / Historical
Rockefeller Foundation
The Rockefeller Foundation was established by act of the New York State Legislature approved by the Governor on May 14, 1913, "to promote the well-being of mankind throughout the world." Between 1913 and 1928 the China Medical Board, the International Health Board, and the Division of Medical Education functioned as divisions of the Foundation, concentrating on the administration of programs in public health and medical education. A Division of Studies was created in 1923 to handle projects outside the medical field. These early years were experimental as the new foundation studied the methods of philanthropy and explored its relationships with other Rockefeller boards.
Although the Rockefeller Foundation is the largest and best known philanthropy founded by the Rockefeller family, it was neither the first nor the last to be established. The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (1901), the General Education Board (1902), the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease (1909), and the Bureau of Social Hygiene (1911) all existed earlier. When the Foundation was created, the Sanitary Commission was disbanded. After the establishment of the Foundation, the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial (1918) and the International Education Board (1923) were created.
The Rockefeller boards and their programs were reconsidered and reorganized in 1927-1928 in order to avoid overlapping programs. The International Health Board of the Foundation was disbanded and an International Health Division was organized. The China Medical Board, Inc., was established as a separately incorporated institution, and the China Medical Board of the Foundation ceased to exist. The Division of Studies was dropped and the Division of Medical Education was phased out. The Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial was combined with the Foundation and the Spelman Fund of New York was chartered to continue activities of the LSRM that were not absorbed by the Foundation. The International Education Board was disbanded.
As a result of this reorganization, the Foundation adopted a program which included public health work (administered by the IHD), the advancement of knowledge in the medical and natural sciences (in part taken over from the IEB), the social sciences (formerly the field of the LSRM), and the humanities and arts (shared with the GEB). The Rockefeller Institute and the Bureau of Social Hygiene were not affected by the reorganization. The program adopted by the Foundation at this time remained basically the same for the next twenty years.
As its files accumulated, the Foundation maintained a card index recording the names of institutional and individual grantees and correspondents. A microfilm copy of this index is available at the Archive Center.
Conditions Governing Access
User copies of minutes microfilm are open for research. Access to the original published volumes of annual reports is permitted.
Scope and Contents
The microfilm contains minutes of the Foundation.
Arrangement
This record group is arranged in two subgroups.
Subgroup 16.1 - Minutes. Subgroup 16.2 - Annual Reports.
Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Philanthropy; Charities; Life sciences; Philanthropy -- United States; Public health; Arts; Medical sciences; Humanities
- Rockefeller Foundation Minutes, 1913-1987; 1
  - Minutes, 1913-1946 (Reel 1)
  - Minutes, 1947-1964 (Reel 2)
  - Minutes, 1913-1918 (Reel 3)
  - Minutes, 1919-1922 (Reel 4)
  - Minutes, 1923-1925 (Reel 5)
  - Minutes, 1926-1927 (Reel 6)
  - Minutes, 1928-1929 (Reel 7)
  - Minutes, 1930-1931 (Reel 8)
  - Minutes, 1932-1934 (Reel 9)
  - Minutes, 1934-1936 (Reel 10)
  - Minutes, 1937-1939 (Reel 11)
  - Minutes, 1939-1941 (Reel 12)
  - Minutes, 1942-1944 (Reel 13)
  - Minutes, 1945-1947 (Reel 14)
  - Minutes, 1948-1949 (Reel 15)
  - Minutes, 1950-1951 (Reel 16)
  - Minutes, 1952-1953 (Reel 17)
  - Minutes, 1954-1955 (Reel 18)
  - Minutes, 1955-1956 (Reel 19)
  - Minutes, 1957 (Reel 20)
  - Minutes, 1958 (Reel 21)
  - Minutes, 1959 (Reel 22)
  - Minutes, 1960 (Reel 23)
  - Minutes, 1961 (Reel 24)
  - Minutes, 1962-1963 (Reel 25)
  - Minutes, 1963-1964 (Reel 26)
  - Minutes, 1965-1966 (Reel 27)
  - Minutes, 1966-1968 (Reel 28)
  - Minutes, 1968-1969 (Reel 29)
  - Minutes, 1970-1971 (Reel 30)
  - Minutes, 1972-1973 (Reel 31)
  - Minutes, 1974-1975 (Reel 32)
  - Minutes, 1975-1976 (Reel 33)
  - Minutes, 1977-1978 (Reel 34)
  - Minutes, 1978-1980 (Reel 35)
  - Minutes, 1980-1982 (Reel 36)
  - Minutes, 1983-1985 (Reel 37)
  - Minutes, 1985-1987 (Reel 38)
- Rockefeller Foundation Annual Reports, 1979-1982, 1985-1987, 1989-1991; 2; 8 Bound Volumes
  Annual reports
  - Rockefeller Foundation Annual Report 1979 (Item REF 361.763 2 ROC 1979)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Annual Report 1980 (Item REF 361.763 2 ROC 1980)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Annual Report 1981 (Item REF 361.763 2 ROC 1981)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Annual Report 1982 (Item REF 361.763 2 ROC 1982)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Annual Report 1985 (Item REF 361.763 2 ROC 1985)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Annual Report 1986-1987 (Item REF 362.763 2 ROC 1986-87)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Annual Report 1989 (Item REF 3610763 2 ROC 1989)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Annual Report 1990 (Item REF 361.763 2 ROC 1990)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Annual Report 1991 (Item REF361.763 2 ROC 1991)